<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great and bloody news from Farthing-Ally in St. Thomas's Southwark, or, The true and faithful relation of a horid and barbarous murther committed on the body of Walter Osily by his own wife on the 31 of this instant July.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1645A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28674</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10736539</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10736539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45582</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45582)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1403:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great and bloody news from Farthing-Ally in St. Thomas's Southwark, or, The true and faithful relation of a horid and barbarous murther committed on the body of Walter Osily by his own wife on the 31 of this instant July.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Osily, Margaret, d. 1680?</term>
               <term>Trials (Murder) --  England --  London.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45582:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:45582:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <head>
               <hi>Great and Bloody News,</hi> FROM FARTHING-ALLY, In St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s SOUTHWARK, Or the True and Faithful RELATJON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Of a Horid and Barbarous MURTHER<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Committed on the Body of <hi>Walter Oſily,</hi> by his own Wife on the 31 of this Inſtant <hi>July.</hi> Who firſt ſtrangled him with a Bow-ſtring, and afterwards cut him with a Hatched on the bare Head, and ſliting his Noſe, giving him a Mortal Wound under the right Ear, with ſeveral other Barbarous Inhumanityes, and how after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhe diſcoverd it to a neighbour, as of her being Apprehended, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion before the Iuſtice of Peace, as likewiſe her Commitment to the <hi>Marſhelſeas</hi> Priſon, where ſhe remains: with ſeveral particulars relating to her Life and Converſation. <date>
                  <add>August :2: 1680</add>
               </date>
            </head>
            <p>WOnderful are the prevailing Inſinuations of Hell to delude poor mortals here below as may be well obſerved in this moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and inhumane murther committed by <hi>Margaret Oſilly</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Husband <hi>Walter Oſilly,</hi> The Relation of which in all its horrid circumſtances being as followeth, her Husband having been abroad on Fryday at the Beargarden, to try a Dog that he had lately purchaſed, came home about nine of the Clock in the Evening ſomewhat diſordered in drink, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding went out with her to a neighbours houſe, where they drank toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, after that they went home ſeemingly well, but it proved not ſo, for the being no ſooner entered the houſe but a quarrel ariſing between them, her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band gave her ſome blows, the which ſhe to outward appearance ſeemed not to regard, but converting her reſentments to private Revenge, the which ſhe in time found opportunity to effect.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45582:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
Her Husband being over powered with drink, falling faſt aſleep ſhe went to a Lodgers Chamber of hers, telling him that her Husband was dead drunk, and that he lay like a Swine upon the Flore, and that he had grievouſly abuſed her, whereupon he perſwaded her to let him alone till he came to himſelf and then to get him up to bed; this Diſcourſe being no ſooner ended but ſhe returned, and locking the Dores cloſe after her, having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked him, got him (as ſhe ſince confeſt) to Bed; where he no ſooner fell aſleep but the Devil prevailing with her prompted her for to commit a Murder that has ſince amazed mankind, for in her ſearch for a miſchievous weapon to work her revengful Rage ſhe chanced to light upon a Hatchet, the which ſhe poiſing in her barbarous hand for ſome ſmall time, at laſt concluded on the Tragecal Exploit, and with a down-right blow ſtruck her ſleeping Husband, who dreamed of no ſuch force, juſt on the Forehead, making there a wound three inches in length and an inch in depth; but not content with that, being deſperately bent on his Deſtruction, ſhe repeated it with a ſecond juſt under his right Ear, the which was about an Inch and a half deep which no doubt was mortal an ſufficient to tranſlate him to immortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and after that another that ſlit his Noſe, and a fourth on his hand between his Fingers, the which he was ſuppoſed to receive in making reſiſtance; after which, as it is verily conjectured, he lying weltring in his Blood and not preſently expiring, ſhe with a Bow-ſtring to make all ſecure ſtrangled him, and ſo put him out of the pain; ſhe being reſolved to perfect the Cruel Deed, and make end in Death. This Bloody exploit being acted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Covert of darkneſs as near as can be conjectured about two of the Clock in the morning, ſhe continuing with the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Corps till the Light appeared, and without doubt oft view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the dreadful Deed her Cruel hands had done, but with what horror I leave the reader to conjecture by the Guilt. About 8 of the Clock ſhe leaving her Husband in the bloody Bed, went to one Mr. <hi>Fowlers</hi> in the <hi>Maze</hi> Yard, where no ſooner entering the Houſe, but ſhe deſired to ſpeak with him in private, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, ſhe declared to him the horrid Murther, and how ſhe had acted it in every circumſtance deſiring him to conceal it or ſome Report to let her bury him privately in his Ninepin Place; and after having drank there, returned home, but he being a man that deteſted inch horrid Impieties, went inſtantly and acqainted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45582:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->one Mr. <hi>Daniel</hi> a Hatband maker, with what ſhe related to him, who delayed not to ſearch into the Truth of this ſtrange report ſo that coming to her Houſe he Knocked at the Dore the which ſhe unwillingly opened, being then ſmoaking a Pipe of Tobacco in her Chair, but at his importunity ſhe aroſe and let him in, who no ſooner entered, but ask'd for her Husband, to which ſhe repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he was gon out, but he did not believe it, for was informed that ſhe had murthered him and that he was reſoved to ſearch, deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Key of the Chamber, the which after ſome denials ſhe delivered to him and thereupon retird into the next Room lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf in, upon which going into the Chamber foun the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Corps lie welterred in Blood all mangled on Flore, where upon he puting his Head out of the Window, called ſeveral neighbours, giving them to underſtand, that there was Murther done in the Houſe, at which ſeveral came in and found the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſpectacle, at which they ſtarted back with horror, ſome of them immediately running for a Conſtable to ſeiſe the Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, whilſt others watched to hinder her from making an eſcape, but in fine ſhe being apprehended was carried before Juſtice <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> where Mr. <hi>Fowler</hi> appeared to give Evidence againſt her who related what ſhe had declared unto him, with many other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whereupon he was bound over to proſecute; It was likewiſe told her that for that horrid Fact ſhe had committed ſhe would be burnt, to which ſhe replied, ſhe burn'd already and that would prepare her for the Flames to come; or words to that effect: after a full Examination ſhe was committed to the <hi>Marſhalſea</hi> Priſon, there to remain till ſhe ſhall be delivered by due courſe of Law the Coroner and his Jury ſitting upon the Corps retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it upon their Inqueſt wilful Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This <hi>Walter Oſſily</hi> was formerly her Apprentice, when upon the Death of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Husband, ſhe married, his time not being out when he was murthered, it was reported that he was very Familiar with her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Life of her former Husband, and that he lay with her the night after he was Buried:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45582:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
He having been married to her about a twelvemonth, in tha<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time as 'tis ſaid, he had ſpent and made away of hers about tw<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hundred pounds, which extravigance of his and the abuſing her a<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is conjectured were the cauſes for which ſhe murthered him for which no doubt ſhe gave him cauſe, being a Woman of a Turbulent Spirit, and living much at Varience with her former Husband who was a Caſtermaker by Trade, of which employ was alſo the perſon now murthered. May this ſad Crime and cruel murther be a warning to all Chriſtians to deter them from the like Barbarity,</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45582:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
